Register of the Firing Line (Television Program) broadcast records 80040.4089238
Hoover Institution Archives
- Episode Guide, 1966-1999
  - "A Firing Line Debate: Resolved: That Women Have It at Least as Good as Men-Part II" Guests: Buckley, William F. (William Frank), Jr., 1925-2008.: Dickey, James.: Sobran, Joseph.: Pilpel, Harriet F.: Fox, Muriel.: Freeman, Erika Padan., 30 November 1982 (Item Program Number S0537, 1226)
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.777
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6711
  - "Nuclear Hysteria?" Guests: Scheer, Robert.: Kinsley, Michael E., 5 January 1983 (Item Program Number S0538, 1227)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 1
    Program details: For so adept an interviewer (it was he who had elicited from Jimmy Carter the news about lust in his heart), Mr. Scheer is a rather overbearing guest. But WFB is able to carve out some space for give-and-take. RS: "We know right now that the command-and-control systems that now exist on either side probably could not last more than 15 or20 minutes in an all-out nuclear war, so really, when you talk about nuclear war, the evidence is pretty clear that you are talking about a situation of extreme chaos, madness--" WFB: "I certainly hope your book is widely circulated in the Soviet Union."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.780
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6714
  - "The Humanities and the Federal Government" Guests: Bennett, William J., 5 January 1983 (Item Program Number S0539, 1228)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 2
    Transcript: Box/Folder 178: 7
    Program details: There is no one that conservatives would rather have seen as chairman of this body if it was to exist--and Mr. Bennett, keeping his claims in proportion, engagingly makes the case for its existence as a tax-funded entity. WJB: "Are there things more important than the humanities? Of course there are. But I don't think we decide the budget for an agency of government based on that.... I think it was Macaulay who said it was more important to bake bread than to have pianos.... But that doesn't mean we should all be baking bread and not have any pianos. A modest amount set aside for the humanities to follow the purposes set out in the legislation and to do so in a review system that is fair... seems to me a desirable and defensible function for the government."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.781
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6715
  - "Buckley's Turn to Explain Himself" Guests: Green, Mark J.: Kinsley, Michael E.: Kondracke, Morton., 24 January 1983 (Item Program Number S0540, 1229)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 3
    Program details: A bracing installment of the semi-annual show in which host and guests change places, with Mr. Buckley being asked to, as the title has it, explain himself mostly with reference to the policies of the President whose election he had championed. Topics range from defense to inflation, with a heavy concentration on Mr. Reagan's tax policies. Two samples: Mr. Buckley: "People paid more [taxes] in 1981 than they paid under Carter." Mr. Kinsley: "Not the people you are most concerned about, the people in the top brackets." WFB: "What makes you think I'm most concerned about them?" MK: "They are the ones whose rates you wanted to reduce down to 25 per cent." WFB: "It's true that they are the ones who agitate most strongly to avoid tax exposure, but 'they' is 37 million Americans, i.e., the people who pay more than 25 per cent." ... WFB: "Mr. Reagan would unquestionably resist an aggressive nuclear attack by the Soviet Union with a counterattack. I don't think anybody in the world doubts it. I happen to think this is the profoundest protective wall that we have."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.782
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00G708158
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6716
  - "Do the Banks Know What They're Doing?" Guests: Davidson, James Dale.: Cline, William., 24 January 1983 (Item Program Number S0541, 1230)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 4
    Transcript: Box/Folder 178: 8
    Program details: The short answer to the title question is: "No." WFB gives some of the background of this show: "In the 17 years since this program began, the producer has not had the equivalent difficulty in getting somebody representing ... an institution to visit with us for the purpose of explaining that institution's policies and defending them. We must have issued two dozen invitations, to the people whose names come obviously to mind when one thinks of international banking. They were all tied up. Like their banks. I do not mean to suggest that we settled for second-echelon guests. Merely that an unapologetic defense of banking policies is not likely to be heard." As indeed it was not, nor of the International Monetary Fund or World Bank, which had encouraged the banks in their disastrous lending to Third World and Iron Curtain countries. An informative and rather frightening show.
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.783
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6717
  - "Ideas and Action" Guests: Rostow, W. W. (Walt Whitman), 1916-2003., 22 February 1983 (Item Program Number S0542, 1231)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 5
    Program details: How does policy get translated into action? How do the different advisors of a decision-maker (say, the President of the United States) maneuver to get their ideas accepted? Mr. Rostow was writing a series of books, each examining a case in point; one of his case studies is the topic of this absorbing hour--President Eisenhower's dramatic "Open Skies" proposal for arms-control verification, launched at the first Geneva summit conference in 1955. WWR: "So at the moment of the summit your duty was not to say, I'm sure Khrushchev will buy this.' All the objective argument was that he would not. But you should make it in total good faith, and I think Eisenhower did make it in good faith.... If you are playing with issues this big, if you could get a breakthrough, it would mean so much to everyone, your own country and to the human race. You don't simply say, 'My analysis of those folks is that they are going to say no.' You keep your powder dry, but you go out and make a fair offer."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.784
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6718
  - "Should the U.S. Withdraw from Europe?" Guests: Solarz, Stephen J.: Barnet, Richard., 22 February 1983 (Item Program Number S0543, 1232)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 6
    Transcript: Box/Folder 178: 9
    Program details: Messrs. Solarz and Buckley start from the assumption that whatever decisions we take vis-a-vis the Soviet Union--whether in terms of troop strength in Europe or in terms of arms control (currently on the table was President Reagan's Zero Option: that the Soviets dismantle their intermediate-range nuclear forces in Europe, in return for our not deploying the Pershing II and cruise missiles)--must be predicated on the need to protect ourselves and our allies. Mr. Barnet starts from the assumption that we are the problem, not the solution. And never the twain shall meet. RB: "I think the Soviet Union has maneuvered itself, largely with the help of this Administration, into a position where they appear to be readier to take the missiles out and to reverse the course and to negotiate than we." WFB: "You must be kidding."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.785
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6719
  - "Confidence and Betrayal" Guests: Cohalan, Florence.: Pilpel, Harriet F.: Tamarkin, Norman R., 22 February 1983 (Item Program Number S0544, 1233)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 7
    Program details: A profound discussion among, as WFB puts it, "a very thoughtful lawyer, a very thoughtful doctor, and a very thoughtful priest" on the subject of their obligations when told a secret that has not only past but future implications. Monsignor Cohalan explains that for priests, "The problem is very simple.... Canon law, which would take precedence in a matter concerning the sacraments, says with the utmost possible simplicity and finality that the seal of the confessional is inviolable, period"--even on pain of jail. In both the legal and the psychiatric professions the law and the ethics are less clear. As Mrs. Pilpel points out, "in some states there are no privileges of a certain type.... If a person is called upon to make a disclosure, he cannot effectively plead a doctor-patient privilege in a state, for example, like Texas, where there is no such privilege." For Dr. Tamarkin, "Here's the problem about this whole issue: it's between two goods, in a way. On the one hand you want the patient to be able to see you as in their corner, on their side. On the other hand, you don't want to see somebody going around murdering other people. So you are caught in between two allegiances."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.786
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00TZ8H5O2
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6720
  - "The Carter Years: Power and Principle" Guests: Brzezinski, Zbigniew K., 1928-, 31 March 1983 (Item Program Number S0545, 1234)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 8
    Transcript: Box/Folder 178: 10
    Program details: Mr. Brzezinski was, as Mr. Buckley puts it, "identified in the public mind as the hawk in Mr. Carter's Administration, the role of dove going to Mr. Cyrus Vance, the Secretary of State." And Mr. Brzezinski is, as ever, hawk like in another sense as well, pouncing fiercely upon points of disagreement, in a conversation ranging from the Carter Administration's "normalization" of relations with China, to Ted Kennedy's behavior in 1980, but starting with Mr. Carter's speech about our "inordinate fear of Communism": "Bill, I was consulted and I even contributed, perhaps in a direct way but at least indirectly, to that very phrase, and therefore let me say what that phrase means. It doesn't mean that one should underestimate the threat of Communism, but it means that in the competition between freedom and Communism, we have nothing to fear--that our system is more viable, more creative, more appealing, that Communism is a waning ideology. And I really think that's historically true."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.787
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6721
  - "Reagan and the Question of Legal Services" Guests: Harvey, William F., 31 March 1983 (Item Program Number S0546, 1235)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 9
    Program details: This show does not do as much as one might have hoped to clarify the dispute over the Legal Services Corporation, but it does offer some helpful perspective on how we might provide legal services to the poor without creating a lawless posse of lawyers like the LSC. Mr. Buckley points out that "there are more lawyers in Los Angeles than there are in all of Japan," but it is Mr. Harvey--who approves the LSC in principle--who tells of LSC lawyers going into Mexico to recruit immigrants "for the purpose of both employment and the direction of law suits against their prospective employers." This, as Mr. Harvey points out, is illegal, but "most restrictions are not self-enforcing ... and they have not been enforced in the past."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.788
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6722
  - "How to Read, How to Figure" Guests: Saxon, John.: Down, A. Graham., 14 April 1983 (Item Program Number S0547, 1236)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 10
    Transcript: Box/Folder 178: 11
    Program details: How can a country spend as much time and money on education as ours does and produce declining literacy and numeracy? Blame partly the theorists, who replaced phonics with the look-say method of teaching reading and who tried, as Mr. Saxon puts it, "to teach a child algebra by teaching him advanced algebraic concepts that had best be reserved for the junior year in college, when he has mastered the fundamentals." Blame also the social engineers, who, as; Mr. Down puts it, have made the schools into "psycho-social devices for solving the problems of our society." A discussion at once gloomy and heartening, with two men who are actively doing something to help--Mr. Saxon, by writing an algebra textbook; Mr. Down, through his own writing and the work of his Council.
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.789
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6723
  - "How to Speak, How to Listen" Guests: Adler, Mortimer Jerome, 1902-2001., 14 April 1983 (Item Program Number S0548, 1237)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 11
    Program details: A visit from Professor Adler is always a treat. On this occasion--sparked by his latest book, How to Speak and How to Listen--he reminds us that real conversation doesn't come naturally. We have to work at speaking clearly and listening attentively just as we have to work at writing clearly and reading attentively. WFB: "What are the responsibilities of the speaker to attract that kind of attention? Should you be able, as a finished listener, to listen to dull people?" MA: "No, any more than you should be able to read well a bad book."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.790
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00ANCWYH2
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6724
  - "The Mess in Central America" Guests: Solarz, Stephen J.: Calero Portocarrero, Adolfo., 3 May 1983 (Item Program Number S0549, 1238)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 12
    Transcript: Box/Folder 178: 12
    Program details: Mr. Calero's personal history tells much of the story. Under Nicaraguan strongman Anastasio Somoza, Mr. Calero was active in political opposition, and was once jailed for his efforts. He had real hopes for the government of "national reconstruction" that succeeded Somoza, but in January of 1983, when it had become apparent that the Sandinistas had consolidated their hold on that coalition government, he fled the country and joined the armed resistance. While Mr. Solarz speaks happily of the prospects of a "negotiated settlement" in neighboring El Salvador, Mr. Calero says: "The Communists don't share power. That's common knowledge. Any neophyte would know that."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.791
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6725
  - "Medical Malpractice" Guests: Moskowitz, Richard.: Rosenblatt, Stanley.: Mannix, Arthur, Jr., 3 May 1983 (Item Program Number S0550, 1239)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 13
    Program details: A lively--though not always good-tempered--discussion of the many issues involved in medical malpractice: "How should doctors be punished when they make a damaging mistake?" Do large malpractice awards punish the culpable doctor or the entire pool of patients whose medical costs will go up? WFB: "It has struck me for years that one very seldom reads about disbarred lawyers, and one very seldom reads about unfrocked doctors, so that to the extent we laymen depend on you all to police yourselves, you don't do a striking job of it. Either that, or most of you are angelic." SR: "Which is hardly the case in either profession ..."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.792
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6726
  - "European Unity?" Guests: Barzini, Luigi., 3 May 1983 (Item Program Number S0551, 1240)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 14
    Transcript: Box/Folder 178: 13
    Program details: Mr. Barzini has the depth of a scholar and the facility of a journalist. Agree with him or not that "Europe should have one common foreign policy, one common defense policy, and one financial policy," he is a joy to listen to. LB: "I quote Helmut Schmidt: 'The Americans are what they are, but they are the only Americans we have.' " WFB: "There wasn't quite enough savoir-faire in Europe to prevent two world wars recently."LB: "I say repeatedly that what the Europeans can contribute is the wealth of their past errors, of their stupid wars, of their senseless convulsions and revolutions."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.793
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6727
  - "A Traditionalist Looks at Modern Europe" Guests: Lowenstein, Hubertus zu.: Livingston, Robert., 13 May 1983 (Item Program Number S0552, 1241)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 15
    Program details: As a man whose property was seized and who was condemned in absentia by Hitler for his first book, Prince Hubertus has standing to speak of Hitler as an aberration in German history. Still, as WFB reminds him and us, as soon as Germany was united, in 1870, it began starting wars. Prince Hubertus: "I wouldn't be alive today if it hadn't been for the Quaker breakfasts which we received after the First World War. [Then] after the Second World War--" Mr. Livingston: "The present chancellor, Mr. Kohl, will be the last German chancellor who will have a living memory of this.... He remembers and refers often in his speeches to the CARE packages and the Marshall Plan aid that he as a young boy received, but his successor will not have the same memories, and I think this is going to be a significant generational change."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.794
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6728
  - "The British Elections" Guests: Wilson, Harold, Sir, 1916-, 13 May 1983 (Item Program Number S0553, 1242)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 16
    Transcript: Box/Folder 178: 14
    Program details: On the eve of Margaret Thatcher's re-election, a detail-filled and sometimes quite delicious session with the man who at that point was Britain's longest-serving peacetime prime minister in this century (a distinction he would eventually lose to Mrs. Thatcher), and who had just that morning retired as a member of Parliament. HW: "We are going through an extremely interesting time. I prefer two-party government, and I always thought that if I couldn't win with a working majority, I hoped the other side would be there with a working majority or Britain wouldn't be properly governed. I won four times, and twice only very narrowly." ... WFB: "Did you train Tony Benn with the others?" HW: "Yes, I brought him up. He was a very sensible boy in those days. I think once I used the phrase lightly, right off the cuff--I said, 'He immatures with age.' I think that has continued to be true."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.795
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6729
  - "The Afghan Mess" Guests: Rahim, Abdul.: Assil, Ayyoub., 26 May 1983 (Item Program Number S0554, 1243)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 17
    Program details: In the fourth year of the Soviet occupation, there were four million Afghan exiles, and an estimated one million had been killed. "Historians," WFB begins, "will perhaps record that the West rallied to the aid of Afghanistan by depleting our representation at the Olympic Games in Moscow in 1980." The two guests speak a slightly unidiomatic English, but they are eloquent in their fervor for their country and their God, and persuasive in their assertion that it would be in other countries' interests to assist them. AA: "The Russians are not coming to Afghanistan as tourists. They are preparing for other countries. They want to reach, as soon as possible, to the Persian Gulf to cut the neck of the oil."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.796
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6730
  - "A Fresh Look at Economic Problems" Guests: Thurow, Lester C., 26 May 1983 (Item Program Number S0555, 1244)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 18
    Transcript: Box/Folder 178: 15
    Program details: A bracing session with a man who has his own strong opinions but who is capable of looking even at them with some perspective: "If you recommend policies that are so sensitive that they have to be put in place exactly as you recommend them ... for all practical purposes you are recommending policies that can't work, for the political process is never going to take one idea and put it in place precisely as Art Laffer or Les Thurow thinks it ought to be put in place." And a salutary reminder: "If you take the real-world scientists--geologists, meteorologists, people who study earthquakes--their prediction records and their ability to control is no better than economists'."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.797
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6731
  - "Is Reaganomics Working?" Guests: Baldrige, Malcolm., 2 June 1983, 12 August 1983 (Item Program Number S0556, 1245, 1245R)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 19-20
    Program details: The economy was looking up, but the budget deficit was still sky-high, there was 10 per cent unemployment, and the dollar was overvalued--or was it-- President Reagan's Secretary of Commerce isn't so sure: "There is still enough pressure to keep the dollar as high as it is because it is the safest safe in the world for investments, and it has still comparatively high interest rates; a combination of those two is what keeps the dollar up." And why is the deficit so high? "Nine out of ten congressmen and senators that I talk to are for lower budget deficits. They all say that it is a big problem. But when it comes to specific actions of where to cut, they've all got a different reason not to cut here or cut there, so the job doesn't get done."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.799
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6733
  - "Is It True That the Well-Qualified Can Find Jobs?" Guests: Navin, Hank.: Malarkey, Thomas., 2 June 1983 (Item Program Number S0557, 1301)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 21
    Transcript: Box/Folder 178: 16
    Program details: The 10 per cent of Americans who are unemployed are not all at the lower end of the ladder. Messrs. Navin and Malarkey had both been on successful career tracks and have each now been unemployed--and very actively seeking employment--for one year. They discuss, with the pain of personal experience, the difficulty of getting a job if you don't currently have a job, and the fact that, as Mr. Malarkey puts it, "You [an unemployed person] are a social pariah." Mr. Navin: "The job is where we spend most of our waking hours, and it forms the content of our character. It is what it is that we are.... It is how we contribute. When you don't have a job, who are you?"
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.798
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6732
  - "Andrei Sakharov's Complaints against the Freeze Movement" Guests: Bundy, McGeorge., 20 July 1983 (Item Program Number S0558, 1302)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 121: 22